Papers from the Isabelle Sayers Collection
Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, Library of Congress
Papers from the Isabelle Sayers Collection circa 1886-1980 1920-1980
Sayers, Isabelle S.
3.7 linear feet (6 boxes)
Recorded Sound Reference Center, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Paper and photographic materials created and gathered by Isabelle S. Sayers as she assembled her collection of early recordings and audio equipment.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Deakins, Duane D.--Correspondence.; Ferguson, Clarence A.--Correspondence.; Green, Lew--Correspondence.; Janis, Elsie, 1889-1956.; Kishpaugh, Grace--Correspondence.; Kishpaugh, Harlan--Correspondence.; Marken, Lawrence McKinley--Correspondence.; Odell, L. Brevoort--Correspondence.; Sayers, Isabelle S.; Sayers, Isabelle S.--Archives.; Walsh, Jim, 1903-1990--Correspondence.
Organizations
Isabelle Sayers Collection (Library of Congress)
Subjects
Sound recordings--Collectors and collecting--United States.; Sound--Recording and reproducing--Equipment and supplies.; Women collectors--United States--Archives.
Form/Genre
Catalogs.; Diaries.; Ephemera.; Letters (Correspondence).; Newspaper clippings.; Notes.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Postcards.; Scrapbooks.
Administrative Information
Collection Acquisition
The papers were donated to the Library of Congress by Isabelle S. Sayers in several increments in 1981, and by Frank T. Sayers in memory of his wife in 1982 and 1987.
Additions
No further additions to the papers are expected.
Access Restrictions
The Papers from the Isabelle Sayers Collection are open for research.
Biographical Note
Isabelle S. Sayers (1914-1982) was an avid collector of early recordings and audio equipment. Sayers's primary interest was in rare items, particularly those from 1884 to 1905 of the early sound recording era. One of the few female collectors of the mid-20th century, Sayers expanded her collection over a period of at least 30 years by placing advertisements in local newspapers and collectors' newsletters, and by developing relationships with collectors and antique dealers nationwide. She displayed and spoke about her collection locally; in 1959 she appeared on WBNS-TV to demonstrate early machines in her collection. Sayers was also interested in inventors of recording equipment: she collected photographs, clippings, and ephemera relating to Thomas Edison, Emile Berliner and their various inventions.
Sayers also had an avid interest in photography and the history of the West. She wrote two books on Annie Oakley: Annie Oakley and Buffalo Bill's Wild West (New York: Dover Publications, 1981) and The Rifle Queen, Annie Oakley (Sayers, 1973). Both incorporated historical photographs from her own collections as illustrations.
Isabelle Sayers resided with her husband, Frank T. Sayers, in Columbus, Ohio, from circa 1953 through 1971. The couple lived in Ostrander, Ohio, from 1971 until Isabelle Sayers's death in December 1982.
Scope and Content Note
These papers were part of the larger Isabelle Sayers Collection, a donation of early disc and wax cylinder recordings, phonographs, and related equipment donated to the Library of Congress in several increments between 1981 and 1987. The Sayers Collection includes some extremely rare items from the incunabula period (1884-1905) of the sound recording era. Among these rare items are 19th-century Berliner Gramophone Company discs, concert grand wax cylinders, and an assortment of playback equipment such as a "player-piano type harmonica." The collection totals approximately 2,000 wax cylinders, 4,000 discs, and 50 antique phonographs, as well as related equipment and assorted objects such as statues of the Victor dog, Edison banks, and old needle tins.
This collection of paper and photographic materials dates from circa 1886 to 1980, but many of the items are undated.
Collection Arrangement
The papers are arranged in six series:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1951-1980
Series 2: Collection Notes, 1919-1972
Series 3: Printed Material, 1923-1977, undated
Series 4: Ephemera, 1907-1977, undated
Series 5: Photographs, circa 1886-1975
Series 6: Oversize Materials, 1897-1965, undated
http://lccn.loc.gov/2008647462
Container List
- Series 1. Correspondence, 1951-1980, undated, .4 linear feet
  Series I consists of correspondence between Isabelle Sayers and collectors, experts, and dealers. The majority of the correspondence relates to the exchange, sale, or appraisal of antique records, cylinders, recording equipment, phonographs, or other equipment. Many of the letters relate both to Sayers's collection and to her personal life, reflecting the close relationships she developed with other collectors and experts.
  Frequent or prominent correspondents represented in this series include Harlan and Grace Kishpaugh, L. Brevoort Odell, Duane D. Deakins, Lawrence McKinley Marken, Lewis G. Green, Clarence A. Ferguson, and Jim Walsh (whose papers are also held by the Recorded Sound Section).
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically; one folder of undated material is filed at the end of the series.
  - Correspondence, 1951-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series 2. Collection Notes, 1919-1972, undated, .21 linear feet
  Series II consists of acquisition notes, equipment descriptions, lecture notes, and other items. Included is a diary dating from circa 1952 to 1959 with notes about Sayers's acquisition of equipment and recordings. Lecture notes and miscellaneous writings refer to the history of recording in the United States and Ohio. Miscellaneous collection notes consist of scraps of paper with brief notations about individual recordings, record lists, and addresses of dealers and collectors. One folder contains notes and ephemera relating to Sayers's interest in vaudeville performer Elsie Janis.
  Materials in this series are filed alphabetically by description.
  - Addresses, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Diary of collection and acquisition notes, 1952-1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Equipment descriptions, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Elsie Janis notes and ephemera, 1919-1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Lecture notes and miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Receipts, 1958-1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous collection notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series 3. Printed Materials, 1923-1977, undated, .42 linear feet
  Series III contains newsletters, journals, pamphlets, guides and other printed materials relating to music, recordings and phonographs. Included are programs for music and theater performances, pamphlets on Thomas Edison's inventions and life, technical equipment guides, radio travel logs, record price listings and small catalogs, and reprints of articles on Ohio music and black recording artists.
  Printed Materials are arranged alphabetically by type and thereunder by title or description.
  - Journals and newsletters
    - The Music Box: An International Magazine of Mechanical Music, vol. 7, no. 1, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Music Box Society Newsletter, no. 4, 1975 March (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Music Memories Monthly, vol. 3, no. 4, 1963 June (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - The Ragtime Society, 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
    - The Ragtimer, 1975 March (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Pamphlets
    - Audio Equipment, 1923-1977 (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
    - Thomas Alva Edison biographical materials, 1928, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Music progams and guides, 1910-1929 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Radio, travel logs, 1925-1963 (Box 3, Folder Oversize 31)
    - Radio technical guides, 1923-1930 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - The Rifle Queen: Annie Oakley, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Record price lists, advertisements, and catalogs, 1930-1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 34-36)
  - Reprints, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Series 4. Ephemera, 1907-1977, undated, .21 linear feet
  Series IV consists of items in a variety of formats relating to Sayers's recording interests. Included are clippings relating to musicians, inventors, and equipment; a calendar issued by the Capehart Collection; advertisements; record inserts from early Edison recordings; greeting cards; pictorial envelopes; phonograph diagrams; and postcards. One folder of miscellaneous materials includes a slide with song lyrics, business cards, and a record coupon.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by format. A folder of miscellaneous ephemera is filed at the end of the series.
  - Advertisements See also Oversize Folder 31, Radio, travel logs, 1925-1963
    - Music box advertisements, 1897-1900, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Phonograph advertisements, 1897-1923 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Piano advertisements, 1897-1909 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Recording advertisements, 1904-1929, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Miscellaneous advertisements, 1898-1939, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Calendar from the Capehart Collection, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Clippings, 1932-1977 See also Oversize Folder 66, Clippings, 1897-1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Please use photocopies in folder 45.
  - Photocopies of clippings (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Please use these photocopies rather than the fragile originals in folder 44.
  - Greeting cards, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Phonograph diagrams, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Postcards and pictorial envelopes, 1908-1947, undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Record inserts for Edison cylinders, circa 1912-1914 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    For cylinders #1828, 1889, 2024, 2034, 2051, 2063, 2142, 2152, 2219, 2269, 2288, 2290, and 2389.
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
- Series 5. Photographs, circa 1895-1975, undated, .42 linear feet
  Series V contains approximately 75 photographs (black-and-white and color) as well as 7 slides and 32 negatives. Many of the photographs in this series were printed from copy negatives of older photographs or images from journals and books. Included are photographs of Isabelle Sayers displaying equipment from her collection and portraits of inventors Thomas Edison and Emile Berliner. Also represented are various actors and musicians, with a particular focus on Elsie Janis, a Columbus, Ohio, native and star of many vaudeville productions. Photographs of recording equipment and phonograph advertisements are also present. Three scrapbooks are included in this series. One contains Isabelle Sayers's family photographs and related ephemera; the two others include portraits and clippings of Broadway, movie, and recording personalities.
  Photographs are arranged alphabetically by subject or type; miscellaneous negatives and photographs are filed at the end.
  - Audio equipment, 1962, undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Emile Berliner portraits and equipment, undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
    Prints made from copy negatives.
  - Thomas Edison and the gravestone of Samuel Edison, 1969, and undated See also Oversize Folder 70, Photographs and prints, 1923 and undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
    One image is a copy.
  - Elsie Janis portraits, circa 1895-1920, undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
    Some are copies.
  - Photographs of phonograph advertisements, undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Portraits of actors and musicians, undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
    Included are images of Helen Clark, Glen Ellison, Kirsten Flagsted, Ada Jones, Helen Jepson, Betsy Lee Shepherd, and Blanche Theborn.
    Most are copies.
  - Isabelle Sayers with collection and musicians, circa 1945-1975 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Scrapbooks, 1886-circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 58-61)
    Includes family photographs, images of Broadway and theater stars, and ephemera.
  - Miscellaneous negatives, undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
    Most are copy negatives.
  - Miscellaneous photographs, 1899, undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
- Series 6. Oversize Materials, 1897-1965, undated, 2.04 linear feet
  Oversize materials include posters, broadsides, photographs, prints, and newspaper and magazine clippings. A small collection of broadsides for early concerts and equipment demonstrations are mostly undated. Oversize photographs are all of Thomas A. Edison or his inventions; also included in this folder are several copies of an undated wood block print of Edison. Clippings related to Thomas A. Edison (a few are full copies of publications focusing on his career or death), Elsie Janis and other musicians. Oversize advertisements are also included.
  - Advertisements, 1910-1923, undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Broadsides, undated (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 5, Folder Oversize 66)
    Photocopies of oversize clippings; please use these rather than the fragile originals.
  - Clippings, 1897-1961, undated (Box 5, Folder 67-68)
    Please use the photocopies of these clippings housed in folder 66.
  - Publications, 1859, 1919-1973 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Photographs and prints, 1923, undated (Box 5, Folder Oversize 70)
  - Posters, circa 1929-1930, undated (Box 6)
    Rolled.
Transferred Materials
Some publications, especially record catalogs, that originally formed part of the Sayers papers have been cataloged separately and added to the Library's general collections.